Finding Aid for Henry Romaine Pattengill papers, 1861-1939
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Romaine Pattengill papers 1861-1939
Pattengill, Henry Romaine, 1852-1918.
1.5 linear feet
852058 Aa 2
School teacher, Michigan Superintendent of Public Instruction; correspondence, subject files, photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was deposited by Mr. And Mrs. Theodore G. Foster (donor no. 1676 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions, 1945-1956.
The collection is open to research.
Henry R. Pattengill was born in Mount Vision, Otsego County, New York, January 4, 1852. The family moved to Litchfield in Hillsdale County, Michigan in the mid-1860s. Pattengill graduated from the University of Michigan in 1874. For the next ten years, he was superintendent of schools in St. Louis and Ithaca, also serving as president of the Gratiot County Teachers' Association, as a member of the Board of School Inspectors, and later on the County Board of Examiners. In 1885, Pattengill became associate editor of the Michigan School Moderator; he later became sole owner and proprietor. From 1893 to 1897, Pattengill served two terms as Michigan Superintendent of Public Instruction. He died November 26, 1918.
The collection is comprised of three series: Correspondence, Other Papers; and Photographs. Included in the collection are scrapbooks, diaries, autograph books, and other materials relating to his public life and various travels. The photographs include portraits of Pattengill and Pattengill family members; group portraits of reunions of students taught by Pattengill in Ithaca, Michigan; and a photo of the Pattengill home in Lansing, Michigan.
Subjects:
Education--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1914.; Michigan Education Association.; Progressive Party (1912); Progressivism (United States Politics); Temperance--Michigan.; Voyages and travels.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Lansing.; Ithaca (Mich.); Lansing (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Michigan. Dept. of Public Instruction.; Pattengill, Henry Romaine, 1852-1918.; Pattengill family.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Schermerhorn, James, 1865-1942.; Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932.; Woodruff, Roy Orchard, 1876-1953.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1861-1865 (Box 1)
  - 1866-1870 (Box 1)
  - 1871 (Box 1)
  - 1872 (Box 1)
  - 1873 (Box 1)
  - 1874 (Box 1)
  - 1875 (Box 1)
  - 1876-1880 (Box 1)
  - 1881-1885 (Box 1)
  - 1886-1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891-1895 (Box 1)
  - 1896-1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901-1905 (Box 1)
  - 1906-1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911-1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916-1920 (Box 1)
- Other papers
  - Essays written for the Websterian Society, Litchfield, Michigan, 1864-1870 and undated (Box 1)
  - Various documents (certificates, mortgages, letters of introduction), 1874-1918 (Box 1)
  - Poetry, 1880-1915 (Box 1)
  - Poetry, undated (Box 1)
  - Thesis entitled "What are we doing?" read before the State Board of Education, July 7, 1882 and other essays (Box 1)
  - Obituaries of Pattengill and material relating to dedication of Pattengill School, 1918-1922 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1906-1932 and undated (Box 1)
  - Reunions of Pattengill's students, 1890-1939 (Box 1)
    (include group photographs)
  - Miscellaneous personal documents, 1875-1918 and undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Travel journals of trip to Mexico in 1898 and to the Panama Canal in 1913 (Box 2)
  - Autograph books, diaries and notebooks of jottings (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook of programs largely of meetings of teachers associations (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook relating to Michigan Press Association trip to Canada, 1898 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Pattengill students reunions, family, and miscellaneous, 5 envelopes (Box 2)